A Guide to the Maury Family Papers, 1786-1995
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Maury Family Papers, 1786-1995
The Library of Virginia
51892
6 cubic feet (14 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William Maury Jones and Anne White Jones, Portland, Oregon.
Biographical Information
Charles Broadnax Maury was born on 29 November 1822. He was the son of William Grymes Maury and Anne Hoomes Woolfolk. He married Sallie Fontaine Maury (1825-1915) in Washington, DC on 19 November 1850. She was the daughter Richard Brooke Maury and Lucy P. Hunton. Following the death of her father, Matthew Fontaine Maury (1806-1873) was appointed as guardian to her and her brother John Minor Maury (1826-1868). Charles Broadnax Maury served as treasurer of the Fire Insurance Company in Washington, DC. He died on 10 February 1906. He and his wife are buried in Oak Hill Cemetery in Washington, DC.
Their son, William Lewis Maury, was born on 30 November 1851. He married Cora Wells Sears (1860-1917) in St. Louis, Missouri, where he was employed as an auditor for a railroad company. They later moved to Palestine, Texas where he worked for the International and Great Northern Railway Company. William Lewis Maury died on 15 December 1927. He and his wife are buried in Bellefontaine Cemetery in St. Louis. They had five children, including Isabel Lee Maury, who married Dr. Thomas Wistar White.
Elizabeth Tunstall White was the sister of Dr. Thomas Wistar White. She was born in Pittsylvania County, Virginia on 21 June 1884. She graduated from Randolph-Macon College (A.B., 1907) and Washington University in St. Louis (A.M., 1916). She was a high school teacher. Elizabeth Tunstall White died in March 1973 and is buried in Green Hill Cemetery in Danville, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1786-1995, of the Maury family of Caroline County and Fredericksburg, Virginia, Washington, D.C., Missouri, and Texas. The collection includes correspondence and subject files of Charles Broadnax Maury (1822-1906) and his wife Sallie Fontaine (Maury) Maury (1825-1915), and their son William Lewis Maury (1851-1927) and his wife Cora Wells (Sears) Maury (1860-1917). There are also genealogical research files and subject files of Elizabeth Tunstall White (1884-1973).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Maury Family Papers.
Series II. Elizabeth Tunstall White Papers.
Contents List
- Series I. Maury Family Papers., Extent: 8 boxes. (Box 1-5, 11-12, 14)
  The correspondence begins in the mid-1820's and includes letters from Lucy P. (Hunton) Maury (1787-1828) in Fredericksburg to her husband Richard Brooke Maury (1794-1840) while he was working in Washington, DC. There is also a group of letters from Richard Brooke Maury to John de Bree (1798-1869) in Norfolk discussing business and naval matters, as well as news of their friend Daniel McCarty Fitzhugh Thornton (1800-1865). Correspondence in the 1840's includes letters from John Minor Maury (1826-1868) to his sister Sallie Fontaine Maury (1825-1915) while he was serving in the U.S. Navy aboard the "Constitution" commanded by John "Mad Jack" Percival (1779-1862). There are also numerous letters from Matthew Fontaine Maury (1806-1873) beginning in 1847 written mainly to Sallie Fontaine Maury and discussing family and personal news. Letters from 1850 to 1870 are mostly between Charles Broadnax Maury and his wife Sallie Fontaine Maury. Correspondence in the 1880's includes a group of letters by Dabney Herndon Maury (1822-1900) while he was serving as minister to Colombia, and there are a large number of letters written by William Lewis Maury in Palestine, Texas to his wife Cora Sears Maury while the she was visiting friends and family in Florida, Illinois, and Wisconsin. Of note are letters relating to the deaths of Matthew Fontaine Maury and Dabney Herndon Maury. The post-1900 correspondence includes letters written by the three sons of William Lewis Maury while they were serving in France during World War I, as well as letters pertaining to his genealogical research, including correspondence with Mary Maury Werth (1844-1928), the daughter of Matthew Fontaine Maury, and Nannie Rose Maury Pollard (1853-1943), the daughter of Dabney Herndon Maury.
  The subject files include appointments and commissions, Bible records, books on the Maury family, Civil War oath, parole, and pardon of John Minor Maury, deeds of the Sears family of St. Louis, diaries, genealogical notes compiled by William Lewis Maury, invitations, photographs, scrapbook, sermons, and sketches, memorials, and biographical materials on Matthew Fontaine Maury.
  - Correspondence
    - 1806. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1822. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1824-1827. (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
    - 1844. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1846-1850. (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
    - 1852-1856. (Box 1, Folder 13-17)
    - 1858. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1860-1863. (Box 1, Folder 19-22)
    - 1865-1873. (Box 1, Folder 23-31)
    - 1875. (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - 1878. (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - 1880-1888. (Box 1, Folder 34-42)
    - 1890-1892. (Box 1, Folder 43-45)
    - 1894. (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - 1900-1903. (Box 1, Folder 47-50)
    - 1906-1913. (Box 1, Folder 51-58)
    - 1915-1927. (Box 2, Folder 1-13)
    - 1943. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Richard Brooke Maury to John de Bree, 1830-1836. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Dabney Herndon Maury to Sallie Fontaine Maury, 1887-1889. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - William L. Maury to Cora Sears, 1886 (June-July, September-November). (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
    - William L. Maury to Cora Sears Maury, 1888. (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
    - William L. Maury to Cora Sears Maury, 1889 (August-September). (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - William L. Maury to Cora Sears Maury, 1892. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - William L. Maury to Cora Sears Maury, 1895 (April). (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - William L. Maury to Cora Sears Maury, 1897 (July-September). (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - William L. Maury to Cora Sears Maury, 1905 (August). (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - William L. Maury to Cora Sears Maury, 1906. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - no date/year. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - no date/year (Cora Sears Maury). (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - no date/year (Lucy P. Maury). (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - no date/year (Matthew Fontaine Maury). (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - no date/year (Sallie Fontaine Maury). (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - no date/year (William L. Maury). (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - no date/year (Thomas Nelson Page). (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - no date/year (Rose Maury Pollard). (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Subject Files
    - Accounts and Receipts. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Address Before Literary Societies of UVA by Matthew Fontaine Maury, 28 June 1855. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - The Albemarle of Other Days by Mary Rawlings. (Box 11, Folder n/a)
    - The Amazing Story of the Maurys in America by Sharon Taylor. (Box 12, Folder n/a)
    - Annual Report - Matthew Fontaine Maury Association, 1920. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Appointment - John Minor Maury, 20 June 1853. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Appointment - John Minor Maury, 16 August 1862. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Bellefontaine Cemetery (St. Louis) Map, 1916. (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Bible Records. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Bible Verses/Religious Writings. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - The Book of Common Prayer and Administration of the Sacraments and Other Rites and Ceremonies of the Church (Two Editions). (Box 12, Folder n/a)
    - The Book of Common Prayer of the Reformed Episcopal Church, 1883. (Box 12, Folder n/a)
    - Certificates. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Christ Church Cemetery (St. Louis) Lot Deed, 1853. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Commission - Sunderland Gregory Sears, 22 September 1862. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - The Confederate Diary of Betty Herndon Maury (copy). (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Corks and Curls, 1907. (Box 12, Folder n/a)
    - The Days of the Upright: A History of the Huguenots by O.I.A. Roche (portion). (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Deeds (Sears Family - St. Louis), 1841-1886. (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Diary - John Minor Maury. (Box 12, Folder n/a)
    - Diaries - William L. Maury. (Box 12, Folder n/a)
    - Diddie, Dumps, and Tot or Plantation Child-Life by Louise-Clarke Pyrnelle. (Box 11, Folder n/a)
    - Diplomas - Cora Hunton Maury. (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Family Record - Fontaine/Maury/Brooke/Taliaferro/Hunton. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Family Record - Charles Broadnax Maury. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Family Record - Dabney Herndon Maury. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Family Record - James Maury. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Family Record - Rev. Matthew Maury. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Family Record - Richard Maury. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Family Record - Sunderland Gregory Sears. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Family Record - Woolfolk/Broadnax. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Family Register of William G. Maury. (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Greeting Cards. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Hair. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Holy Bible (Three Editions). (Box 12, Folder n/a)
    - Huguenots. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - In Memoriam: Matthew Fontaine Maury, 1873. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Intimate Virginiana: A Century of Maury Travels by Land and Sea edited by Anne Fontaine Maury. (Box 11, Folder n/a)
    - Invitations. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - John Walker Maury: His Lineage and Life by William A. Maury. (Box 11, Folder n/a)
    - License to Carry Firearms, 1865. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Matthew Fontaine Maury - Sketches, Memorials, etc. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - The Maury Family Tree by Sue C. West. (Box 11, Folder n/a)
    - Memoirs of a Huguenot Family by Rev. James Fontaine. (Box 11, Folder n/a)
    - Miscellaneous. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - "A Narrative of My Life For My Family" by Francis T. Brooke, 1849. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Oath - John Minor Maury, 28 October 1865. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Obituaries. (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Ordination Certificate of Rev. Matthew Maury (copy), 24 August 1769. (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Parallel Genealogies of George Washington, Robert E. Lee, and William Grymes Maury by William L. Maury. (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Pardon - John Minor Maury, 27 October 1865 (copy). (Box 4, Folder 23-25)
    - Parole - John Minor Maury, 24 July 1865. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Pew Deed, St. Paul's Church (Norfolk, VA), 28 March 1830. (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Photographic Portraits of Men of Eminence, 1864. (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Photographs. (Box 4, Folder 23-25)
    - Photographs (Oversized). (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Physical Survey of Virginia: Preliminary Report by M.F. Maury, 1869. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Pocket Dictionary of the English Language,1872. (Box 12, Folder n/a)
    - Program - 300th Anniversary of Virginians Sailing From England to Virginia, 19 December 1906. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Recollections of a Virginian by General Dabney H. Maury (2 copies). (Box 11, Folder n/a)
    - Scrapbook. (Box 5, Folder n/a)
    - Sermons. (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - Some Prominent Virginia Families - Corrections. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Sons of the American Revolution. Texas Society. Paul Carrington Chapter No. 5. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Suit Papers. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - A Tale of the Huguenots or Memoirs of a French Refugee Family, Translated and Compiled from the Original Manuscripts of James Fontaine by One of His Descendants. (Box 11, Folder n/a)
    - Title Abstracts. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - The University Monthly: A Journal of School and Home Education, April 1872. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Wedding Announcements and Invitations. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series II. Elizabeth Tunstall White Papers., Extent: 7 boxes. (Box 6-10, 13-14)
  This series consists of genealogical research files compiled by Elizabeth Tunstall White (1884-1973) on the allied families of Allen, Anderson, Anthony, Bagley, Irvine, Lewis, Pugh, Rives, Savage, Townes, Tunstall, and White and others. There are abtracts and transcriptions of deeds and other land records, marriage records, military records, parish and church registers, published sources, tax records, tombstone inscriptions, wills and estate administration records, as well as correspondence with numerous descendants, especially Claudia Kelsall Townes (1861-1940), family charts, and genealogies compiled by others. In addition, there are subject files which include books, clippings, Colonial Dames application papers, genealogical charts, miscellaneous research notes, photographs, and poetry.
  - Genealogical Research Files
    - Adcock. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Allen-Anderson. (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    - Anthony. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Austin. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Austin-Richardson. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Bagley. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Ball. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Banks. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Barker. (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Barksdale. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Booker. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Boyd. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Calmes. (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Childers. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Crawford. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - DeGraffenreid. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Duncombe. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Dunnavant. (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Dymoke. (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Holcombe. (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Hopkins. (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Hudson. (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Irvine. (Box 6, Folder 24-28)
    - Lawson. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Lewis. (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
    - Ligon. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Lockett. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Maclin. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Man. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Martin. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Meriwether. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Poindexter. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Pride. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Pugh. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Ragland. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Reade. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Remy. (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Rives. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Robins. (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Savage. (Box 7, Folder 19-21)
    - Sears. (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Spragins. (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Staples. (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Townes. (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Townes - Bible Records. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Townes - Census. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Townes - Coat of Arms. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Townes - Land Records. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Townes - Marriage Records. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Townes - Military Records. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Townes - Miscellaneous. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Townes - Obituaries. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Townes - Order Books. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Townes - Tax Records. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Townes - Wills and Estate Administration Records. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Tunstall. (Box 8, Folder 14-15)
    - Tyng. (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Walker. (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Warner. (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Warner-Lewis. (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Welch. (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - White. (Box 8, Folder 21-24)
    - White. (Box 9, Folder 1-5)
    - Whitlow-Whitten. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Woodson. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Woolfolk. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Subject Files
    - Bedford County VA County Court Abstracts. (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Clippings. (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
    - Colonial Dames Application. (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Colonial Dames Application Proofs and Affidavit. (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence. (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - De Namin' ob de Twins and Other Sketches From the Cotton Land by Mary Fairfax Childs. (Box 13, Folder n/a)
    - "Design and Construction of the Jamestown Ships" by Robert G.C. Fee. (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Eastern Shore Lines. (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Expenses in England. (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - The First Tunstalls in Virginia and Some of Their Descendants by Whit Morris. (Box 13, Folder n/a)
    - Genealogical Charts. (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Hanover County. (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Henrico County. (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - "The Historic Tea Party of Edenton, October 25th, 1774" by Richard Dillard, MD. (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - The Hymnal as Authorized by Approved for Use by the General Convention of the Protestant Episcopal Church in the United States of America. (Box 13, Folder n/a)
    - Indians. (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Labels for Family Pictures Framed by Isabel Maury White, 1952. (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Lawn and Garden Book (Ortho). (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Letter of Credit, 1927. (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - The Letters of Junius (Vol. II). (Box 13, Folder n/a)
    - Lewis, Robert (Framed Photograph). (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Magna Carta and Translation. (Box 14, Folder n/a)
    - Mayflower Line of Descent. (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Miscellaneous Research Notes. (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - "A Missouri Interlude" by Anne Rives White. (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - A Page From the Past: Pittsylvania Court House One Century Ago - 1846 by Maud Carter Clement. (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Parish Records in Virginia. (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Photographs. (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Photographs. (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Poetry/Verses. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Reliques of the Rives (Ryves) by James Rives Childs. (Box 13, Folder n/a)
    - Rison, Mrs. Whitmell Pugh. (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Social Life of Virginia in the Seventeenth Century by Philip Alexander Bruce - Abtracts. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - "Tearin' Through the Wilderness": Missouri Pioneer Episodes 1822-1885 and Genealogy of the Watkins Family of Virginia and Missouri by Marie Oliver Watkins and Helen (Hamacher) Watkins. (Box 13, Folder n/a)
    - Townes, Claudia Kelsall. (Box 10, Folder 6-7)
    - Virginia State Highway Map, July 1937. (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Welsh Genealogical Terms. (Box 10, Folder 9)